Fabio Miranda

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR, DEPARTMENT OF COMPUTER SCIENCE, COLLEGE OF ENGINEERING

University of Illinois at Chicago

851 S. Morgan St, MC 152, Chicago, IL, 60607

□ (+1) 347-545-6405 | ■ fabiom@uic.edu | ★ fmiranda.me

Research Interests

I am interested in developing techniques that allow for the interactive visual analysis of large-scale data, combining methods from visualization, data management, machine learning and computer graphics. I have worked closely with domain experts from different fields and the outcome of these collaborations included not only research published in leading venues, but also systems that were made available to experts in academia, industry and government agencies. My work has also received extensive coverage from different media outlets, including The New York Times, The Economist, Architectural Digest, Curbed, among others.

Education

2012 - 2018 Ph.D. in Computer Science

New York, NY, USA

New York University (NYU)

Advised by Professor Cláudio T. Silva.

Dissertation: "Data structures for the interactive visual analysis of urban data".

2009 - 2011 M.S. in Computer Science

Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil

Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro (PUC-Rio)

Advised by Professor Waldemar Celes.

Thesis: "Volume rendering of unstructured hexahedral meshes".

2005 - 2009 B.S. in Computer Science

Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil

Federal University of Minas Gerais (UFMG) Advised by Professor Luiz Chaimowicz.

Professional Experience

Fall 2020 - present University of Illinois at Chicago

Chicago, IL, USA

Assistant Professor, Department of Computer Science, College of Engineering

Fall 2018 - Fall 2020 New York University

New York, NY, USA

Postdoctoral researcher

Development of new techniques for the interactive visualization of different types of large-scale data, such as streaming timeseries data and image data. Also responsible for mentoring PhD students.

Summer 2016 Argonne National Laboratory

Lemont, IL, USA

Research intern

Mentor: Venkatram Vishwanath

Developed a visualization tool to explore high-resolution volumetric weather simulations, focused in the Chicago metropolitan area, in order to understand the impact of built environment on the city climate.

Summer 2015 IBM T.J. Watson Research Center

Yorktown Heights, NY, USA

Research intern

Mentor: Bruce D'Amora

Developed a web-based graph visualization tool for the exploratory visualization of bitcoin transactions.

Summer 2014 AT&T Research

Middletown, NJ, USA

Research intern

Mentors: Lauro Lins and James Klosowski

Developed a distributed version of *Nanocubes*, a datacube-based approach for the visualization of massive spatiotemporal datasets.

FABIO MIRANDA · CURRICULUM VITAE

Summer 2013 Sandia National Laboratories Albuquerque, NM, USA

Research intern

Mentor: Patricia Crossno

Developed an adaptive kernel density estimation approach for scatterplots using GPUs.

2009 - 2012 **TecGraf / PUC-Rio**

Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Research assistant Mentor: Waldemar Celes

Developed an unstructured hexahedral volume renderer for a data visualization and analysis software

used in most of Brazil's oil fields.

Awards

2018 SIGMOD Best Demonstration Award

For "Interactive Visual Exploration of Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Sets Using Urbane".

2018 Pearl Brownstein Doctoral Research Award

For doctoral research that shows the greatest promise, awarded by NYU.

2010-2012 CAPES and Petrobras Fellowships

Awarded during M.S. studies.

2006-2009 FINEP and CNPq Fellowships

Awarded during B.S. studies.

Selected Media Coverage

September 2017 Urban Pulse Uses Social Media Data to Show Cities in a New Light

Architectural Digest 🗷

September 2017 New program wants to improve cities with the power of tweets and Flickr uploads

Curbed 🗹

December 2016 Mapping the Shadows of New York City: Every Building, Every Block

The New York Times 🗷

October 2016 Listen to the music of the traffic in the city

The Economist 🗹

Publications

2022 CitySurfaces: City-scale Semantic Segmentation of Sidewalks Surfaces

M. Hosseini, **F. Miranda**, J. Lin, C. Silva

Sustainable Cities and Society (accepted)

Visualizing Simulation Ensembles of Extreme Weather Events

C. V. de Souza, P. Luz, M. Cataldi, F. Miranda, M. Lage

Computers & Graphics (minor revision)

2021 Visualizing Environmental Justice Issues in Urban Areas with a Community Input Approach

J. Flax-Hatch, S. Srabanti, F. Miranda, A. Sambanis, M. Cailas

2nd Spatial Data Science Symposium

Sidewalk Measurements from Satellite Images: Preliminary Findings

M. Hosseini, I. B. Araujo, H. Yazdanpanah, E. Tokuda, **F. Miranda**, C. Silva, R. M. Cesar Jr *2nd Spatial Data Science Symposium*

COVID-19 EnsembleVis: Visual Analysis of County-level Ensemble Forecast Models

S. Srabanti, G. E. Marai, F. Miranda

12th Workshop on Visual Analytics in Healthcare

Transportation Scenario Planning with Graph Neural Network

A. A. Peregrino, S. Pradhan, Z. Liu, N. Ferreira, F. Miranda

10th International Workshop on Urban Computing

UrbanRama: Navigating Cities in Virtual Reality

S. Chen, **F. Miranda**, N. Ferreira, M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, C. Brenner, C. Defanti, M. Koutsoubis, L. Wilson, K. Perlin, C. Silva

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (accepted, to appear)

Urban Mosaic: Visual Exploration of Streetscapes Using Large-scale Image Data

F. Miranda, M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, M. Hosseini, G. Dove, C. T. Silva 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems.

Learning Geo-Contextual Embeddings for Commuting Flow Prediction

Z. Liu, F. Miranda, W. Xiong, J. Yang, Q. Wang, C. T. Silva

Thirty-Fourth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence.

2019 Shadow Accrual Maps: Efficient Accumulation of City-Scale Shadows over Time

F. Miranda, H. Doraiswamy, M. Lage, L. Wilson, M. Hsieh, C. T. Silva

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 25, no. 3, pp. 1559-1574, Mar 2019.

Featured on The New York Times

Time Lattice: A Data Structure for the Interactive Visual Analysis of Large Time Series

F. Miranda, M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, C. Mydlarz, J. Salamon, Y. Lockerman, J. Freire, C. T. Silva *Computer Graphics Forum, vol. 37, no. 3, pp. 23-35, Jun 2018.*

Interactive Visual Exploration of Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Sets using Urbane

H. Doraiswamy, E. Tzirita Zacharatou, **F. Miranda**, M. Lage, A. Ailamaki, C. T. Silva, J. Freire 2018 ACM SIGMOD Intl. Conf. on Management of Data - Demo.

Best Demonstration Award

Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Analysis: A Visual Analytics Perspective

H. Doraiswamy, J. Freire, M. Lage, F. Miranda, C. T. Silva

IEEE Computer Graphics and Application, vol. 38, no. 5, pp. 26-35, Sept/Oct 2018.

TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Spatiotemporal Datasets

F. Miranda, L. Lins, J. Klosowski, C. T. Silva

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 24, no. 3, pp. 1394-1407, Mar 2018.

2017 Urban Pulse: Capturing the Rhythm of Cities

F. Miranda, H. Doraiswamy, M. Lage, K. Zao, B. Goncalves, L. Wilson, M. Hsieh, C. T. Silva *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 23, no. 1, pp. 791-800, Jan 2017.*

Featured on The Economist, invited to SIGGRAPH 2017 TVCG special session

Data Visualization Tool for Monitoring Transit Operation and Performance

A. Kurkcu, F. Miranda, K. Ozbay, C. T. Silva

5th IEEE Intl. Conf. on Models and Technologies for Intelligent Transportation Systems (2017).

2016 TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Spatiotemporal Datasets

F. Miranda, L. Lins, J. Klosowski, C. T. Silva

Data Systems for Interactive Analysis (DSIA) 2016.

2012 Volume Rendering of Unstructured Hexahedral Meshes

F. Miranda, and W. Celes

The Visual Computer Journal, vol. 28, no. 10, pp. 1005-1014, Oct 2012.

2011 Accurate Volume Rendering of Unstructured Hexahedral Meshes

F. Miranda, and W. Celes

24th Sibgrapi Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (2011).

Illustrative Volume Visualization for Unstructured Meshes Based on Photic Extremum Lines A. Rocha, **F. Miranda**, and W. Celes

24th Sibgrapi Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (2011).

Funding

Spring 2022 - Spring 2023

PRESUR: Planning a Resilient and Equitable State Using

Real-time Data

Co-PI, \$125,000 (total)

Discovery Partners Institute

Teaching Experience

Fall 2021 CS594: Big Data Visualization & Analytics

University of Illinois at Chicago

Graduate course. No. of students enrolled: 29.

Average student evaluation score: 4.4 / 5.0 (n=25, std. dev.=0.76)

Course page 🗹

Spring 2021 CS425: Computer Graphics I

University of Illinois at Chicago

Undergraduate course. No. of students enrolled: 41.

Average student evaluation score: 4.03 / 5.0 (n=33, std. dev.=0.98)

Course page 🗹

Advised Students

2021 - Ph.D. students (adviser)

University of Illinois at Chicago

Kazi Omar, Marius Horga, Sanjana Srabanti (co-adivising with G. Elisabeta Marai)

2021 - M.Sc. students (adviser)

University of Illinois at Chicago

Soham Pradhan

2021 - Undergraduate students (adviser)

University of Illinois at Chicago

Daniel Hodczak, Jayanth Podapati

2018 - Ph.D. students (mentor)

New York University

Zhicheng Liu (CS PhD student at Southeast University, China), Maryam Hosseini (Urban Systems PhD student at Rutgers), Shaoyu Chen (CS PhD student at NYU), João Rulff (CS PhD student at NYU).

Selected Invited Talks and Presentations

April 2021 Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: Beyond Flatland

Online

Department of Energy Computer Graphics Forum 2021

Department of Energy

April 2021 Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: A Computational

Porto Alegre, RS, Brazil

Perspective on Cities

Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul

Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: A Computational

Niteroi, RJ, Brazil

Perspective on Cities

Fluminense Federal University

Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable

Insights

New Orleans, LA, USA

Portland, OR, USA

Tulane University

Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable

Insights

March 2021

February 2020

January 2020

Portland State University

Fabio Miranda · Curriculum Vitae

4

December 2018 Exploration of Street-Level Images at Scale New York City, NY, USA

Pedestrian Movement Technology Showcase at Metro North

Shadow Accrual Maps: Efficient Accumulation of City-Scale

November 2018

Berlin, Germany

Shadows over Time

IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS)

June 2018

Time Lattice: A Data Structure for the Interactive Visual

Brno, Czech Republic

Analysis of Large Time Series

EG/VGTC Conference on Visualization (EuroVis)

October 2017 TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Phoenix, AZ, USA

Spatiotemporal Datasets

IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS)

September 2016 **Visualizing and Exploring Urban Data**Boston, MA, USA

Data Visualization Summit

October 2016 TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Chicago, IL, USA

Spatiotemporal Datasets

Data Systems for Interactive Analysis Workshop (DSIA)

Academic Services

Conference and workshop

organization

VIS 2021, Local co-chair (2021)

The Future of Global-Scale Spatial Data Collection and Analyses on Urban (in)Accessibility for People

with Disabilities Workshop, Co-chair (2021)

Program committees EuroVis (2022)

Visualization and Data Analysis Conference (2022)

Sibgrapi (2019, 2020, 2021)

IEEE VIS Short papers (2019, 2020, 2021)

Grant reviewer NSF Reviewer (2022)

Discovery Partners Institute grant reviewer (2021)

Journal reviewer IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics

IEEE Transactions on Big Data

IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Transportation Systems

The Visual Computer Journal

Transportation Research Record Journal International Journal of Geo-Information

International Conference on Pattern Recognition

Conference reviewer IEEE VIS (2018, 2019, 2020, 2021)

Sibgrapi (2018, 2019, 2020, 2021)

VLDB (2021) WWW (2021)

University Services

Departmental committees Faculty Search Committee (2022)

Graduate Admission Committee (2020, 2021)

Reviewer Provost's Graduate Research Award reviewer (2020)

WCP committees Carla Floricel (2021), Md Nafiul Alam Nipu (2021), Andrew Wentzel (2021), Muhammad Abdul Wahhab (2021)

Master's project committees

Parikshit Solunke (2021), Pavana Doddi (2021)

Professional Memberships

Association for Computing Machinery (ACM). Brazilian Computer Society (Sociedade Brasileira de Computação, SBC).